<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The A. B. C  set forthe by the Kynges maiestie and his clergye, and commaunded to be taught through out all his realme All other vtterly set a part as the teachers thereof tender his graces fauour.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1547</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09738</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110721</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846211</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846211</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11162</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09738)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11162)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 20:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The A. B. C  set forthe by the Kynges maiestie and his clergye, and commaunded to be taught through out all his realme All other vtterly set a part as the teachers thereof tender his graces fauour.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Wyllyam Powell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1547?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alphabets --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="alphabet">
            <pb facs="tcp:11162:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11162:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The A. B. C</hi> ſet forthe by the Kynges maieſtie and his Clergye, and commann<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be taught through out all his Realme. All other vtterly ſet a part as the teachers thereof tender his graces fauour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
               </seg> A. a. b. c. d. e. f. g. h. i. k. l. m. n. o. p. q. r. r. ſ. s. t. u. v. w. x. y. z. &amp;. &amp; : Eſt. Amen.</p>
            <p>A. B. C. D. E. F. G. H. I. K. L. M. N. O. P. Q. R. S. T. V. W. X. Y.</p>
            <p>A. B. C. D. E. F. G. H. I. K. L. M. N. O. P. Q. R. S. T. V. W. X.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <div type="Sign_of_the_Cross">
               <p>In the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the holye Ghoſte.</p>
               <p>So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Pater_Noster">
               <pb facs="tcp:11162:2"/>
               <head>The prayer of our lorde.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr father which arte in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, halowed be thy na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me. Thy kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e come. Thi wil be done in earth as it is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Giue vs this day our dayly bread. And forgyue vs our treſpaces, as we forgeue them that treſpace agaiſt vs. And let vs not be led into temtacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs from euill. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Ave_Maria">
               <head>¶ The ſalutation of the Aungel to the bleſſed virgin Marye.</head>
               <p>HAyle Mary ful of grace the lord is with the. Bleſſed art thou amonge women, and bleſſed is the fruite of thy Wombe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Apostles_Creed">
               <head>¶ The Crede, or xii. articles of the Chriſten faythe.</head>
               <p>I Beleue in god the father all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighti maker of heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; erth
<pb facs="tcp:11162:2"/>And in Ieſu Chryſt his onely ſon our lord which was conceaued by the holy ghoſt, borne of the virgin Mari, ſuffered vnder ponce Pylat was crucified, dead, buryed, &amp; deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded into hell. And the thyrde day he roſe ageyne from death. He aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded into heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſitteth on the right hand of god the father almyghty. From thence he ſhal come to iudge the quicke and the deade.</p>
               <p>I beleue in the holy ghoſt, the holy Catholyke church, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſayntes, the forgyuenes of ſinnes The reſurrection of the body, and the lyfe euerlaſtynge. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Ten_Commandments">
               <head>The x. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of almighty god.</head>
               <p>THou ſhalt haue none other Gods but me. Thou ſhalte not haue any graue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> image, nor ani likenes of any thyng that is in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen aboue, or in earth beneth, or in
<pb facs="tcp:11162:3"/>the water vnder the earth, to thin te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to do any godly honour or wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Thou ſhalt not take the name of the lord god in vayne. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that thou kepe holy the Saboth day. Honor thi father &amp; thi mother. Thou ſhalt do no murder Thou ſhalt not commit adultery. Thou ſhalt not ſteale. Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witnes ageynſt thy neybour. Thou ſhalt not vniuſtly deſire thy neybours houſe, nor thy neibours wife, nor his ſeruant, nor his mayde, nor his oxe, nor his aſſe nor any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g that is thy neybours</p>
               <p>LOrde into thy handes I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de my ſpirite, Thou haſt redemed me lorde god of truthe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="grace_before_dinner">
               <head>¶ Grace before dynner.</head>
               <p>THe eyes of al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges do loke vp and truſt in the O lord, thou giueſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meate in due ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb facs="tcp:11162:3"/>Thou doeſt open thy hand, &amp; filleſt with thy bleſſynge euery lyuynge thinge. Good lord bleſſe vs &amp; al thy giftes which we receiue of thy bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous liberalitie, through Chryſte our lord. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of eternal glory make vs parteners of the he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly table Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. God is charitie, &amp; he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dwelleth in charitie, dwelleth in god and god in him. God grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs all to dwell in hym. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="grace_after_dinner">
               <head>¶ Grace after dynner.</head>
               <p>THe god of peace &amp; loue vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chſafe alway to dwel with vs. And thou lord haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. Glory, honour, and praiſe be to the O god, which haſt fed vs from our tender age and gyueſte ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to euery liuing thinge, reple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhe our herts with ioy &amp; gladnes that we alway hauig ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t may be rych &amp; ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiful in al good works
<pb facs="tcp:11162:4"/>kes through our lord Ieſu Chriſt Amen.</p>
               <div type="prayer_sequence">
                  <p>Lorde haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
                  <p>Lorde haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
                  <p>Our father which art in heuen. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Let vs not be led into temptacion.</p>
                  <p>But delyuer vs from euyll.</p>
                  <p>Lorde here my prayer.</p>
                  <p>And let my cry come to the From the fiery dartes of the deuill both in weale and wo, our ſauiour Chriſt be our defender, buckler, &amp; ſhelde. Amen.</p>
                  <p>God ſaue the church our king and realme, and god haue mercy vpon all Chriſten ſoules. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="grace_before_supper">
               <head>Grace before ſupper.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lorde Ieſu Chriſt without who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothinge is ſwete nor ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uery, we beſech the to bleſſe vs and our ſupper, &amp; with thy bleſſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb facs="tcp:11162:4"/>to chere oure hartes, that in al our metes and drinkes we may taſt &amp; ſauour of the, to thy honour and glory. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="grace_after_supper">
               <head>Grace after ſupper.</head>
               <p>BLeſſed is god in all his gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes And holy in al his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. Our helpe is in the name of our Lorde, who hath made both heauen and earth. Bleſſed be the name of our lorde. From henſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth worlde without ende.</p>
               <p>MOſt mighty lord and merci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful father we yeld the harti thankes for our bodely ſuſtenance requiring alſo moſt intierly thi gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious goodnes ſo to feede vs with the fode of thy heuenly grace that we may worthely glorify thy holy name in this lyfe, &amp; after be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the life euerlaſtig, through our lorde Ieſus Chryſt. Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11162:5"/>
God ſaue the Churche, our kynge Queene &amp; the Realme, &amp; god haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoules. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="129" type="Psalm">
               <head>De profundis clamaui. <bibl>pſal. cxxix.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the depth I called or the (O Lord) lord heart my voyce. Let thine eares gyue good hede to the voyce of my prayer.</p>
               <p>If thou lorde wylt loke ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon ſinnes, O lorde, who ſhall abyde it.</p>
               <p>But with thee is mercye, and for thy law I haue ſuffered the o lord My ſoule hath abyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his word my ſoule hath truſted in the lorde. From the mornynge watch vntyll night let Iſraell truſt in the lorde.</p>
               <p>For with the lorde there is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and with hym is plenteous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
               <p>And he wyl redeme Iſrael from
<pb facs="tcp:11162:5"/>all his iniquities.</p>
               <div type="prayer_sequence">
                  <p>LOrde haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs.</p>
                  <p>Lorde haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
                  <p>Our father which art. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Let vs not be led into temptacion.</p>
                  <p>But delyuer vs from euyll.</p>
                  <p>Lord giue thy people eternal reſt.</p>
                  <p>And euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g light ſhine vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>From the gates of hell</p>
                  <p>Lorde deliuer theyr ſoules.</p>
                  <p>I truſt to ſe the goodnes of god</p>
                  <p>In the lande of the lyuynge.</p>
                  <p>Lorde heare my prayer.</p>
                  <p>And let my crye come to thee.</p>
                  <p>ALmighty God &amp; moſt holy father lorde both of the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge &amp; of the deade, merciful to all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that leane vnto the by loue and beliefe, we humbly beſech the, that all thy people lyuynge here in this world, &amp; they alſo that be deceaſed
<pb facs="tcp:11162:6"/>into another worlde in thy name by thy merciful clemency, may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne pardon for all theyr ſinnes, and fynally the ioyes of the lyfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtynge, through our Lorde Ieſus Chryſt. Amen.</p>
                  <p>¶ Confitemini domino quoniam bonus. Quoniam in ſeculum mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordia eius.</p>
                  <p>COnfiteor deo beate Marie, omnibus ſanctis: et vobis, peccaui nimis in cogitacione locu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, &amp; opera mea culpa, precor ſanctam mariam: et omnes ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos dei et vos orare pro me.</p>
                  <p>MIſereatur veſtri omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens deus, et vimittat vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis omnia peccata veſtra liberet vos ab omni malo ſaluet et confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met in bono et ad vitam perducat eternam, Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="catechism">
               <pb facs="tcp:11162:6"/>
               <head>¶ Theſe queſtions the maſter ought to demaunde and to lerne his ſcolers.</head>
               <p>SPeke my good chyld. Tel me what art thou.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The chylde aunſwereth.</label>
                  <lb/>
¶ As concernynge my fyrſt byrth, I am a creature of God endewed with wyt and reaſon, the ſon of Adam. And as touching my newe and ſeconde byrth, I knowledge my ſelfe to be a Chryſtian.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The queſtion.</label>
                  <lb/>
wherfore ſaieſt thou, thou art a Chriſtian</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The aunſwere.</label>
                  <lb/>
¶ Bicauſe I am Chriſtened in the name of the father, the ſonne, and the holy ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The queſtion.</label> ¶ what is baptiſme.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The anſwere.</label> It is called the lauer or water of regeneration, by the which euery one that beleueth is receaued and conſecra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted into the felowſhip of Chriſtes Church, to be partaker of the lyfe euerlaſtynge.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ Queſtion.</label> In whom beleueſt thou.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ Aunſwere<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </label> I beleue onely in god the father almyghty, &amp; ſo for the as the Crede ſpeaketh.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ Queſtion.</label> ¶ what is fayth.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ Aunſwere.</label> Fayth is a ſure confidence
<pb facs="tcp:11162:7"/>und truſt of mynde, truſtyng &amp; beleuynge in the very lyuynge god.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion.</label>
                  <lb/>
¶ Howe many Gods are there.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The anſwere.</label>
                  <lb/>
There is but one god a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone for all ſufficient, whiche hath his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge of hym ſelfe, and all creatures haue theyr beinge of hym.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The queſtion.</label>
                  <lb/>
¶ Howe manye perſons byn there in the godheade. ¶ The aunſwere.</p>
               <p>There are three perſons which is god the father, god the ſonne, and godde the holye ghoſt, thre perſons in trinitie, and one god in eſſence. ¶ The queſtion. What is god. ¶ The aunſwere. God is he of whoſe goodnes &amp; by whoſe power I am perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded &amp; aſſured thorow my faith to receaue all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good is, vnto whom alſo I flye in all aduerſities &amp; perils, as vnto a preſent al a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is ſufficict helpe for me, he pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bydeth our turninge from ſinne: ful of mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy, gentyl, good, redy alwayes to forgiue, ſuffereth no ſinne to be vnpuniſhed, &amp; that vnto the third and fourth generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vntill none of that ſinfull flocke be left alyue.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The queſtion.</label>
                  <lb/>
¶ In whom beleueſt thou.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11162:7"/>
                  <label>The aunſwere.</label>
I beleue in god the father almyghty ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker of heauen and earth, &amp; in Ieſu Chryſte his onely ſonne our lorde. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The queſtion.</label>
                  <lb/>
What meaneſt thou by this fyrſt article.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The aunſwere.</label>
                  <lb/>
¶ I beleue that he is my god and mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full father vnto me, tenderynge me as his dere beloued chylde, and to be euermore vnto me an almyghty helper.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The queſtion.</label>
¶ What meneſt thou by the third, fourth fyfth, and ſyxt articles. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The aunſwere.</label>
                  <lb/>
¶ I beleue that Chryſt was conceaued, borne, and ſuffered for my ſinnes, and that he aroſe to make me ryghtuous.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>☞ The queſtion.</label>
                  <lb/>
What thynge worketh this fayth in thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The aunſwere.</label>
It worketh in me loue to God, and to my neyghbours, as to my ſelfe, &amp; ſo changeth me into a newe man, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now I beleuing and knowynge god to haue ſhewed ſo exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge loue for me, and ſtudy to do his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes,
<pb facs="tcp:11162:8"/>and am full heauy in my harte that I can not fulfyll them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="catechetical_instruction">
               <head>¶ Then when the chyld is come to diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, let hym be induced to knowe what god is.</head>
               <p>GOd is myght, wyſedome, and infinite goodneſſe, without beginninge &amp; with out endyng, truth, vnchangeable, iuſt, and mercyful, only god in thre perſons the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the ſon and the holy ghoſt, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al thynges be, by whom al thynges be made and created. And by whom all thynges be gyuen to vs, and in the lyfe to come.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ It is alſo neceſſary to knowe what man is.</head>
                  <p>¶ Man is created after the lykenes of the Image of God. And throughe the ſinne of our fyrſt father Adam, is made pore, vyle wretched, ignorant, inconſtant, frayle, and redy to ſin, ful of Ipocriſie, and vainglory, and redy to fall into eternall dampnation. All this folowethe after that we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued and borne into this worlde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>☞ A godly rule of the true and Chriſtian religion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11162:8"/>
TO ſerue God frely, euen from the harte. To bere his Croſſe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey our rulers, to profyte al men and hurt no body, to truſt in the merites of Chryſtes paſſion, to be ſaued from ſinne, and none otherwyſe, this is the onely and beſt religion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer_to_the_Trinity">
               <head>¶ Here after foloweth an inuocation vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the holy Trinitie.</head>
               <p>HOly Trinitie be helpinge vnto me. O God in thy name ſhall I lyft vp mine handes, the triumphant croſſe of the paſſion of our Lorde Ieſu Chryſte. Ieſus of Nazareth, kynge of the Iewes, ſonne of God haue mercy vpon me. In the name of the father, the ſonne, and the holy ghoſt. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="preprandial_grace">
               <p>¶ Grace before dynner or ſupper.</p>
               <p>PRayſed be thou our moſt mercyful and heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father which of thy ineſtimable goodnes haſt gyuen thy moſte deare belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſon Ieſus to paynefull deathe for our ſakes, thereby not all onely delyuering vs and all faythfull from euerlaſtynge deathe and damnation, but alſo purchafynge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs euerlaftynge lyfe, ioy, and felicitie.
<pb facs="tcp:11162:9"/>endue we beſeche thee thy holy ſpirite into our hertes, that we may dayly more and more walke and go forwarde in the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt path ways of thy ryghteous lawes and commaundementes. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postprandial_grace">
               <head>After dynner or ſupper.</head>
               <p>NOwe you haue well refreſſhed your bodies, remembre the lamentable af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and miſeries of many thouſands of your neigh bours and brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſt viſited by the hand of god, ſome with mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tal plages and diſeaſes, ſome with impry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, ſome with extreme pouertie and neceſſitie, ſo that ether they can not or they haue not to fede on as ye haue done, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre therfore how much and how depely ye preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to the goodnes of almigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty god, for your health, welth, libertie, and many other his benefites giuen vnto you.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <hi>GOD SAVE THE KYNGE</hi> the Queene and the Realme, and ſend vs peace in Chriſt Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Wyllyam Powell.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11162:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
